[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is howard chu
howard shear has been writing free in
open source software since the 1980s
his work has spanned a range of
computing topics including most of the
gnu
utilities for example gcc
gdb gmat etc
networking protocols and tools kernel
and file system drivers and focused on
maximizing the useful workflow system
howard founded simus corporation with
five other partners in 1999
and serves as a cto his current focus is
database oriented covering ldap protocol
lmdb and other non-relational database
technologies
howard welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything i missed in your
bio that you'd like to add
i think that covers it for now yeah
that's quite an extensive list
cool so today's show is
on a pretty meaty topic called b plus
tree data structures and they keep
coming up in
other related software engineering radio
shows we touched on them in
my first show that i did for software
engineering radio with you on lmdb
we did it summon episode 454
with thomas richter on postgres as an ol
ap database simon riggs on postgres
episodes 362 and database engines
episode 415 so
someone has to try and tackle the topic
and
i know you're an expert in it so here we
go
okay i think because it's so complex i'm
gonna split the show into three parts
we're gonna dig into what tree
algorithms are b trees lay the
foundation
move on to b trees in a bit of depth
from what's involved and then
probably halfway through the show we
should have enough
laid down to tackle b plus trees so here
we go i'd like to start with an overview
our tree algorithm is its terms and its
history so we can lay a good foundation
i'll then move us on to b trees and
finally on to b plus trees
so what do we need to understand first
well alright so these data structures
are used
to quickly search for items in a large
data set
and
the tree structure
is used because it
allows you to
search more quickly than for example
just a
linear list layout
and um
how would you describe a
tree algorithm is that where you can
search things quickly or
well it's it's called a tree just
because of the
the logical way the data is arranged
you start with a
central root point
and then it branches out
two different levels
to cover the entire span of the data
range
so if you're just to think about a
regular tree in the ground the root
would be the trunk and you turn it
upside down and think about from
yeah
so the computer science version of a
tree is upside down from what you would
see in nature yes okay i'll keep that
image in my head
so there's a few terms coming up that
you know have a stab at um so we can try
and break these up
so what's a binary search tree
okay so that would be
the most fundamental you know the
starting point for most of these tree
designs
and it's based on the
a simple search algorithm where
let's go back to our
flat list
let's say you have a list of 100 items
and you want to find one specific item
in that list the slow way to find it is
to just start at the beginning of the
list and check every element until you
find the one you're looking for
and on average it will take you
one half of the number of elements in
the list to find
the item you want so if you've got 100
items on average it will take you 50
lookups to find what you're looking for
okay
so
we can
we can improve that drastically using a
binary search in binary search you take
whatever list you have
and you
examine the element in the middle
right so if we've got our 50 items sorry
if we have 100 items we look at the 50th
item and see
you know is it the one we're looking for
and sorry i forgot to mention that this
only works if the list is in sorted
order right
so you go to the halfway point you find
the 50th item you see is this what i
want if not you see
say is it higher or lower than what i
want
if it's higher than what i want then i
go and divide
the next interval down so
from the middle of the 50th i go down to
the 25th
okay so at each point if i don't find
what i'm looking for
i can either go
higher or lower and divide the next
interval in half
and so that that's the essence of a
binary search
and
the way this
the way this improves things is that
every step
you eliminate
at least one half of the elements from
consideration
so it's it'll get you to the one you're
looking for much faster than a simple
linear search
excellent i think you've answered my
question of why we need
a tree algorithm and binary search tree
so is there a particular
time
you would use them or
you know a certain type of data or does
it matter
it could be used with any kind of data
so the the other thing
that gets us to the tree structure so
first of all what i described as binary
search
is how you execute it if you have a flat
linear list right but you can basically
encode all of those
halvings and
subdivisions by rearranging your flat
list
into a tree structure right so at the
root of the tree you put your
50th element and then at the two
children of
that you put on the left half say you
put the lower 50 items and the right
half you put the
upper 50 items and then at each level
below that you subdivide
and keep on branching out and the other
thing to point out is
you know every element every node in
this binary tree has
up to two children
yeah i was just trying to visualize that
see just how if you imagine
the root is a dot and then you draw a
triangle shape with a dot at the top and
then two dots on the other side join
them together that's your triangle and
they're the two
two leafs
two children as it were
if you have the dot and draw a straight
line down
at most you're going to split that into
two and then have two more dots split
them down again
so
maybe like um visualize a um deck of
house of cards you know when you're
stacking cards well yeah yeah very
similar yes so you've got the two cards
waiting to get at the top with the one
card base
and then every end of the card is
another two points of a card isn't it if
you if you're looking at that front on
you'd see the root structure and the two
points
yeah exactly
yeah that's
good i just figured that on the spot
that's a good good analogy
so you're asking why do we need them or
when do we use them
yeah how and when is it used
the original the generic binary tree
that we just described you know these
days it's only used as a teaching tool
to give you the idea
of what you're trying to accomplish you
know in practice
a plain binary tree
has a lot of uh
management problems
so
it really isn't used in real life
you know it's you it's
it's used in computer science classes to
teach you about binary searches
okay well that's at least it helps us
discuss the terms
which we've touched on a route being the
base of that tree or the top of the
house of course
a leaf is that
joining a root to the next node to the
next leaf would be the bottom most a
terminal node
and anything between a root and a leaf
is generally called a branch
okay okay so is that enough foundation
to understand what a b tree is do you
think or
should
you know that covers binary trees so
i as i alluded to you know there are
some problems when you work with just a
plain binary tree and that would lead us
into you know discussing bee trees
would you want to touch on some of the
problems i know it's academic but
yeah well the first thing is
you know it's easy to con construct a
binary tree if all of your input data is
already sorted when you begin okay
but if you're
if you have a very naive algorithm that
says
for example you start with
a node with any particular value and you
want to insert the next node
and you could say is the new node less
than
the current node or is it greater than
the current node and if it's less you
make it the left child and if it's
greater you make it the right child if
you actually start with a perfectly
sorted
input data set then this very simple
binary tree construction algorithm
will
actually
give you a
linear linked list because
every new node will always be
either greater than
okay say you have a list that's sorted
in ascending order then every new node
will always be greater than the one that
preceded it so every time you do an
insert you'll always insert onto the
rightmost branch and so
you'll get a degenerate tree which
actually looks like a straight line
which is
not very useful
for the other search properties of the
tree yeah because the left
the left
leaf
is the lower side and the right leaf is
the upper side so
if everything's
higher than the previous one then you're
only going to be popular in the right
side aren't you that's right yeah you'll
never populate the left side so this is
one of the problems with a plane binary
tree is that it's very easy to get into
these degenerate forms that aren't
balanced right and if it's not balanced
then you don't get any advantage of the
binary search properties
yeah where you split it in half and look
at the higher or lower because there's
never a lower
exactly so you'd be better off just
going back to the
original way and counting
yeah yeah and so that's the most
fundamental problem that motivated you
know the uh the development of
something like a bee tree
and this isn't new is it it's been
around
yeah it's it's been around at least
since the 1970s yeah i think the first
first published paper uh is 1971 or 72.
okay just before we move on to what
b-tree issues
solve can we just revisit a root a leaf
and a a node
was that the right word root leaf and
they're all nodes right there's a root
node there's a leaf node and there are
branch nodes in between yeah yeah
so a leaf is yeah you describe it again
i won't get in the way
so all right so the root is you know the
starting point right and the leaf is a
terminal point there's a leaf has no
children
okay that makes more sense it's the end
of the line right
and anything that
is
you know interposed anything that
connects between the root and the leaf
is a branch
okay and a
a node can only have two branches
in a binary tree yes i know it can only
have two branches okay and if it has
your children that's a leaf yeah
a node can have up to two branches it
could have zero it could have one
and that could be a right or left
depending on whether the value is higher
or lower i think
we had a good start but covering the
basics
and the history there so if we feel
ready
let's move on to the main types of b3
so what is a balanced tree if we could
revisit that
okay so you know we mentioned that you
know if you just naively construct a
binary tree and you have
data of a particular arrangement for
example sorted in ascending order then
you won't have a very good tree
structure maybe it won't be balanced
and it won't give you any search
advantages
so
you know this problem was recognized
pretty early on and people thought about
ways to
to make the tree structure
self-managing and self-balancing so that
as you insert data to it you know it
always
manages to
check its own status
and rebalance things as necessary
and rebalancing in this case
means actually changing the shape of the
tree
you know for example let's say i
i construct a tree with three nodes
right and i'm just inserting the values
one two and three
and if i start naively by just say
saying
uh i insert node one
and then i insert node two and since two
is greater than one i put it on the
right child
and then i insert nodes three and three
is greater than two so
i may put three as the right child of
two okay so now i have
a three a three node tree that's a
straight line right
and
a rebalancing operation in this case
would look at that tree and say well
that's no good
we're going to rotate it left by one
position
so that
node number two becomes the root
the node number one becomes the left
child and node number three is still the
right child of node two
and then we have a perfectly balanced
tree
yeah i'm thinking of um
might be totally irrelevant but you know
when you go to a website and they've got
one of those looks like molecule
structure when your mouse hovers over it
and moves about
kind of like one of those where you've
started with the root as one
and then two three so you just drag
number two and put that at the top and
then you've got one below it and three
reforming
the
tree structure yeah i get that that
makes sense so
what we just described is a balancing
operation
and the idea
is to you know develop an algorithm that
manages a tree structure so that it
balances itself automatically
so that it it can do the analysis that
we just described
and just automatically keep a tree
balanced
and the b tree is actually only one of
several ways that have come up you know
in in computing to solve this problem to
solve the self-balancing problem
and two other ones that are very common
again they're they're taught early on in
computer science courses you know is
a red black tree and an avl tree
so
let me just chat about those two
where we talk about an algorithm that
rebalances the tree
some practical
way of that might be
there's an
insert value and part of that function
looks to see what is there already and
then make some decisions and
gives you an okay but behind the scenes
it's rejig things
is that how that sort of looks
behind the scenes it's rebalancing
yeah yeah so you have an api that you're
using to insert
a child or a value
and then part of the algorithm and the
library that you're using looks
everything behind the scenes and
rearranges it but gives you like a
return value of one or okay or something
yeah you know generally it's
for example in the case of a b tree
it will attempt to do the insert first
and then fix up anything that needs to
be fixed up afterwards
okay so i'll take the data as quick as
possible and then
i mean you know the effect is the same
because
you know the caller will have to wait
for whatever clean up or rebalancing to
finish before
the api returns
okay just like a normal api okay um
since you mentioned those other two
types of trees
that you're familiar with
if you can give us a bit of information
about that that'd be great
well they're they're both
improved versions of a binary tree
for example in an avl tree
first of all we were talking about
binary trees where we inserted a node
with a with a simple value right node
with a value 1 a node with a value 2 and
a node with a value 3. in an avl tree we
add
a little extra information to each node
we call it a balance factor so
when you insert a value into a node or
into the tree it goes into a node and
the node starts off with a balance
factor
say of zero that says it that means it's
balanced
and
if you add a left child to it it might
get a balance factor of minus one that
says okay there's something on the left
side
or if you add
a child on the right side it might get a
balance factor of plus one meaning that
it's got a child on the
right side
and
the algorithm that maintains the tree
will go up and down examine these
balance factors and if the balance
factor ever exceeds
plus one or
minus one like if the balance factor
gets to two or it gets to minus two then
then it knows oh this tree is now too
heavy on one side and it'll know that it
needs to rebalance it that's the basic
idea behind
an avl tree
and is that how to be value something
what does the avl stand for as i recall
they were the initials of the people who
invented it okay so just a name
yeah just a name
a red black tree is
is actually named you know they maintain
balance factors as well but they they
name them as colors red and black but
it's the same general idea
okay
rm array
how do i say this
mre search trees
okay
so
so far we've been talking about a binary
search tree where every node can have
two children right an m-ary tree is
where any node can have
that's just collecting children sorry to
interrupt that's just collect why it's a
binary search tree because there's only
you know one of two values
that's it yes this is more from me this
episode okay
so yeah binary cert you know binary
search tree is
a branch factor of two
you know any node can have up to two
children and then
m area tree is just the more generalized
form where any node can have up to m
children where m is whatever
you know arbitrary number that you want
to assign it to
but they have to be equal don't they
they have to
all
levels of the tree need to have up to
that amount
that's right yeah
you know this we're going to
diverging soon from
typical computer science teaching on
this
as we go a little further into this but
but for now okay we're talking about b
trees and
a fixed branching factor branch factor
being the the maximum number of children
a particular node can have yeah we
should probably just stick to e3
okay
um so i think we touched upon
logarithmic and big o notation in our
first show together and probably quite
across quite a few other shows we've
done on software engineering radio we
would just like to give a
summary of that because
that's what this all brings us isn't it
that's how it's all measured
sure well yes the big o notation
basically
you know you'll see capital o and
parentheses and some factor inside and
that means
you know semantically means on the order
of right so if you say something is
big o of log n that means
the complexity of that
function is on the order of a
logarithmic value
a logarithm of the number of elements
so
you know if we look at our very first
example of the linear search
you know in big o notation that's big o
of n where the
complexity of searching that element
searching that structure
is
basically equal to the number of
elements in the structure
so it's a form of notation to let you
know how
fast or slow something's going to be
well how complex something is which
usually means how fast or slow it is
yeah uh you know the the larger the
number the slower it is
and so
you know the logarithm of n is
always smaller than the value of n
and and it increases much more slowly
than n itself increases right and so
that's that's a very desirable property
in algorithm because it means the
complexity grows very slowly that means
as
data volumes increase
the performance decreases very slowly
you know ideally you would want the
performance to not decrease at all but
this is normally the graph that starts
level and then
curves up near the end or the other way
around
when you see
starts and
curves up slowly yeah yeah that's right
so
b3
is a balanced tree that's just a short
way of it of saying isn't it
yeah it's it is one of the
self-balancing binary trees yeah yeah
except it's not it's not necessarily
binary right it's it's m area it's an
arbitrary factor
okay
and is there a
proven statistic of how fast they are
you know if you follow that structure
well it you know it is a logarithmic
algorithm you know it's big o of log n
and the base of the logarithm just
depends on you know the m the branch
factor
if you have
a binary
if you have a b tree that has
you know m equals two then it will be
this is log of base two
if you
give it a branch factor of four then you
know it'll be o log to base four
and then
how would you decide
between
a binary tree and you know
instead of two nodes some larger factor
yeah
so that is really
that's really a judgment call that needs
to be tuned for the use case because one
thing you're tr well you're trading off
a couple of things here
the more
branches the more yeah the more elements
you can pack
to a node more branches you can put to a
node the fewer nodes you need
okay
but
you know the
the larger a node becomes
you know the more work it takes to
maintain
the pointers inside
you know so
like if i have a node that has
a hundred elements
that would be slower to manage than the
node that only has four elements
yeah and if the
if you're doing
i think anyway this is just how i'm
understanding it if you've got a binary
tree and the node's just got two
children
and
the right leaf is the higher value on
the left but then if you go to four or
seven or whatever you've got to then
order all those in the right
way don't you of each number yeah you
have to keep all of them sorted and you
have to
you actually have to execute a binary
search within that node to find what
you're looking for
yeah so
and you've got to keep that all in your
head as you're thinking about it when
you write the code
yeah
generally you're going to find you know
in examples in textbook examples of a b
tree that
you know the
they'll pick some fixed number and and
never worry about it again it'll be like
okay we're going to do
8 nodes or 16.
16 leafs per node or whatever and and
then just forget about it you just
set it and
not worry again
and is it something that
you would come back and revisit at some
point or
well
you know we're talking about the general
b tree here when when we get to b plus
trees
you know
those those considerations go out the
window so okay
so we've talked about
a b tree we know we're gonna move on to
our b plus tree
but there's a b minus three can you tell
us a bit about that
oh no b minus three is just
another way of writing b3 that's
maybe it's a type of
minor
okay we've covered logarithmic time
so a b3 is well suited for storage
systems that read and write relatively
large blocks of data such as disks
do you agree with that
i think that's more
uh more suitable for b-plus tree
a b-tree
the general form of a b-tree
it can be
tailored for
block storage and and the idea again is
you make
your nodes the same size as your disk
blocks
okay yeah so this is the actual link of
getting back to
file systems and why it's used there yes
okay that makes sense so if if the block
size which nowadays is 496. kilobytes
isn't it
4096 bytes yeah right yeah
and that would be your biggest
leaf node what would that be
that would be the size of your node yeah
yeah
in the b tree all of your nodes should
be the same size
okay so
let's start the big one
so just to recap we've gone over
a binary search tree
so that's a
a root node
and then children
each uh leaf can have
two children left and right
the right generally the higher value and
the left is the lower
and everything sort of founded upon that
we've moved on to balanced trees
so there's always a left and the right
we've discussed big o and logarithmic
time
and the current uses for b trees
now we're going to move on to b plus
trees
right
so let's start again
what is the b plus 3 data structure used
for
today
it it finds a lot of use in all kinds of
data management applications
for example in many
say sql databases
relational databases a b tree is almost
always used for indexing
and in some cases it's also used for
primary data tables
and
why is that
well it's always used for indexing
because you know it is
a structure it's an ordered structure
right so
it's uh
it's fast to look up elements in
and
you know it lets you
move
sequentially
through the data set so if you want to
retrieve elements in this sorted order
in a particular range it's very it's
very well suited for that
in for the primary data sets
it's not always used
because
you know generally
a b plus tree
has
range limits on the sizes of items you
can put into it
so
while you might have data with
relatively small keys say
you know eight byte integer keys
if you're
attaching
say a 200 megabyte value to that key
you know it may not
be so easy to manage in a b plus tree
and so you might use a different data
structure to store the actual
data that goes with the keys
okay um what relation so it was a say it
was a simple key value
store you're trying to implement
what relationship does the b3
are half to the key and the value
is the is the node a key or is the key
just a bit of data in that tree
okay so if we back up and look at you
know what we talked about in b trees you
know
we actually were using a much more
simplified example where a node only
contained a single value like an integer
right one two or three
so in in that case in the terms that
you're talking about
it would be
a key only database
okay yeah because the only thing we were
storing in there was
a searchable value that was a key
in the case of the b plus tree
you know we have those keys those
numeric keys
but we can also associate with them
an arbitrary blob of data
and
in a b plus tree structure
you know the
only the leaves of the tree actually
store
the data values
all of the root and interior
uh nodes
will always store only the keys
okay so your
the key coming in for example in a
database search
part of
a select and because you've got an index
created
form
where such and such equals something
then you know that's the key so then you
can
reliably predict how quickly that's
going to take you know it's going to be
fast
if you find an index which will then
recover the value which is the the row
where the information stored
yeah
and again you know in
if you're using a b plus tree only as an
index then
the value that you get back is just
going to be a pointer to the data that
lives somewhere else
right
yeah i think i'm getting it now
and again there's the alternative where
you actually use the b plus tree to
store the primary data as well you know
in that case the value that you retrieve
will be you know the complete data item
that was associated to that key
yeah because if you've got a quick look
up and the index
you want still want a quick way to find
the actual data you're asking for
as well so
you would
you could potentially have the two b
plus trees like you just said
yeah
okay we can move on to question three
[Laughter]
so what extent is adoption driven by
some of the newest hardware like ssds or
newer types of memory for
this tree structure does that do they
have to change it for
where blocks are stored or anything like
that or is that sort of transparent
you know it's
a lot of the answer to that question
depends on
what the operating system is doing with
the different memory structures or the
you know the newer types of memory as
you were talking about you know there's
persistent memory or
like obtain
memory or some other things like that
you have you have the option of
making that
memory transparently
usable
or you have the option of making it an
explicit block device
so
it really depends on what the operating
system has done one of the things that
we we didn't
state
explicitly here is that in
in the b plus tree again we're talking
about nodes
or yeah nodes that are the size of disk
blocks right and yeah in the b plus tree
terminology we're gonna we're going to
call those pages okay so one page of a b
plus tree
equals one page in a file system one
page on disk
yeah i think um
thinking back to the lmdb show
and we were talking about
cpu caches and all sorts of things like
that
keeping the data
that can be held in cache small and that
is
what you're trying to do here isn't it
yeah that's why we only store keys in
the interior pages
and keep
the actual data at the leaf
that means you can fit the maximum
proportion of the
key index
in memory
so you're not always having to go back
to the file system to get the keys
right
yeah so when you're doing key lookups
they can all be in memory and very fast
and then when you actually you know get
to the bottom of the tree and find the
value that you want then you might
actually have to go out to disk
or some other slower storage
and that's the idealized case right but
obviously if you have a very small
database it could all be entirely in
memory and if you have a very large
database you could wind up with you know
portions of the
interior index also
just pushed outside of memory
and
when we're talking about
a b plus 3 data structure
obviously that's a thing but what does
that thing look like on
on a computer or
a hard disk
well there's you know there's certainly
a lot of leeway in how you construct it
you know at the bits and bytes level but
conceptually
it's not much different than the b tree
right
you have a root
page the root page can have
some number of pointers in it to
children
and in this case as i mentioned before
we no longer talk about it as an mary
tree
it's
as many
child pointers as will fit
in a page
so it's not a fixed number
it's just you you cram in as much as
will fit before you have to overflow
into a new page
okay
i'm still asking some really basic
questions here sorry
um so is is this data structure
constructed from something on a file
system
or in a text file or something like that
how do i
my question's coming from thinking about
the data.mdb file you know that lmdb
creates in the first show we did
together
what's inside that you know what's
inside well
that is a
just a sequence of pages
and each page you know has pointers to
other pages
okay
so in in the textbooks
they will give you an example of a
b-plus tree where
you know all of the dimensions are fixed
constants you know it'll say
you're going to create a b-plus tree
where every key is eight bytes long and
there are
eight keys per page
that's it you're done in the real world
you know keys can be various sizes and
because the sizes vary that means the
number of items that you can fit per
page also varies
so
this is where
like a database engine like lmdb
departs from
what the textbook tells you
because the textbooks give you a very
simplified version
where
you know there's there are no variables
and
in reality you
need to accommodate you know
keys and
records of varying sizes yeah real world
data
can you revisit and provide a simple
description of a b plus tree
okay
so if that's a thing
yeah it's
we'll start again we have a root page
which can have
for example you know a list of up to
eight pointers two children
right
and the children will be
pages as well so all of the pages are
always the same size
so a branch page
again points to more children
and then at the bottom of the tree you
have the leaf page
which
points to actual data and within each
page
of the root or the branch pages you have
the only thing that you store in those
pages are keys
keys and a pointer to the next level
down
or the next thing that you're looking
for
does that make sense yeah i was just
following it down my my brain there
and b 3 is a replacement for b trees or
are they just different options yeah i
would say it's a replacement you know
you find
b plus trees being used everywhere and b
trees not so much
okay well we don't really need to
discuss trade-offs between them if
everyone just uses b plus 3.
we touched on it before you know the
main the main reason is
that by
keeping all of the
data values at the bottom leaf pages you
get more keys in memory which is that
should be the smaller
structure for that small that's right
and we've touched on um
our dbms's sql databases that use them
for
primary keys and actually looking up
the data that the keys point to as well
can you think of any
bigger products examples
that use them
or is it mainly just indexes
yeah well um you know for example
sql lite uh you know
uses b plus trees for its indexes and
for some of its tables as well
obviously open ldap uses lmdb so that's
using b plus trees for
indexes and for you know main data
the other popular databases postgres
uh is
based on b plus trees
mariadb or mysql they're actually using
something called
i sam
completely different structure
yeah that's right i've seen that a few
times
okay are there any places that
you think could benefit from people's
trees where you don't see them
mainly in the database world
i'm gonna guess that
you know the database world has been
around this for long enough you know
they know pretty well
where they can leverage it i would say
in databases they're already using it
where it needs to be
and um
have we touched upon the term height
when we talk about leaf nodes
heights
well
height is just you know a description of
you know how many
levels of pages are in the tree you know
yeah so how big the house of cards could
be how many exactly yeah so if you if
you have a tree that's just a single
root page then you've got a height of
one there's there's nothing going on you
know if that root has
just a bunch of leaf
pages immediately under it then it's got
a height of two
if it's got
a root page and then some branch pages
and then immediately under that some
leaf pages then we've got a height of
three
so
okay
and um
do you have any tips on how to keep
where you're working on in your head
while you're dealing with these is it
best to
visualize things
write some sketches down or do you just
get used to them when you're doing it
i suppose sketching on paper when you
need to but you know
or when you're using a library doesn't
matter
it doesn't matter you know when you're
using the library all you care about is
here insert this key and here
find this key and give me this value so
yeah you don't really care what what the
structure looks like underneath
and um
you did your own b plus 3 algorithm
didn't you
for l
yes yeah
you obviously know the front end and the
back end of that thing
were there any um lessons learned or
tips if
or warnings to never do it yourself you
know
if someone's thinking about it
you know your takeaways from actually
doing the b plus three algorithm
yourself
first of all
as i mentioned before what you learn in
the textbooks
is only a very simplified version of
what you're going to need in the real
world so if you want to write one of
these yourself you'll be prepared
for
the textbooks to not tell you everything
you need to know
and then
you really need to have an extremely
good reason
to write this yourself because they're
at you know at this point there are many
libraries available and you
probably should just use one that exists
off the shelf
yeah i think it's the the old
profile and benchmark if or look at
stuff as and when if um there's an issue
with something
yeah
just to trust that that person or that
company or team
knows what they're doing
right you know what you know ten years
ago when i started writing lmdb you know
the the things that we wanted it to have
obviously did not exist off the shelf
so
that prompted me to write it but
i'd say it's it's hard today to find a
use case that's not well covered by an
existing library
yeah i think
people are doing new things
tend to reinvent things and forgot that
there's probably something already there
that was designed
20 years ago they just haven't done
enough research
there as well and there's there's so
much tendency to
just
reinvent
and are you quite strict with yourself
for
trusting someone else has done it better
than you you know you you've got a very
strong reputation of you know speed and
performance and getting the best out of
things
have you had to have words with yourself
to not go down that route
it's it's always the last resort you
know always always i search for
something
that exists that you know that would fit
my needs before sitting down to write my
own tool
yeah also i think that's good advice for
any of the listeners so
i think we've talked on a couple of my
questions already i was gonna ask why b
plus trees are used for indexing and
table indexes and that's because
i'll try and recap
they've got predictable
times for searches and finding things
and they're
very efficient at key value operations
so
yeah they're they're actually optimal
for
searches there's
you'll always get the lower lower bound
of
search times yeah
and um
okay so
with the b plus tree
is it complicated to get the data into
it in the first place you know how how
would you put a ton of data into a b
plus tree
truck track
oh is it complicated well
no we're doing a whole show on it so
yeah it's complicated
there you go
it's certainly you know it's not as easy
as the plain binary tree
it's not as easy as some of the other
self-balancing
trees but one of the advantages again
that it has since it uses these
relatively large pages is
you know as you insert records into it
it has a fairly s
fairly low
rate of new allocations right every time
you allocate a new page it's good for
you know 20 30 50 elements before that
fills up and you're forced to allocate
another page
so it's got pretty good efficiency in
that respect as far as
resource constraints
okay
that makes sense
i've got a question from one of the
other hosts here um how do we handle
concurrency control in data bit bases
that use b plus tree
there's a lot of different ways to
handle that
so that would be
somebody
two processes trying to insert data with
using the b plus three library and it
hasn't quite finished
putting that data in the right place so
yeah
that's the easy way to understand it
so there's
this is one of those
topics that
you know like it has multiple different
approaches okay
there's the very simple approach which
actually lmdb uses which says we lock
the entire tree
for one writer
and we don't let go of it until that
right is completely finished so
in that sense we actually have
no concurrency for rights
there's always only one writer at a time
and as i said you know this is very
simple
and it's
a decision
that you thought about changing at any
point
no no no that's that that's a decision
that was reached after
quite a bit of experience with other
concurrency schemes and did you have to
make a trade-off for that or
is there a statement
off in some ways you know as as you get
to
much larger databases
you might see that your overall right
throughput could be slower than
optimal
it really tends to depend on the right
patterns
another approach
that for example berkeley db uses
is to use
lock coupling
that is
as you
navigate down the tree from the root to
the leaf where you need to insert data
you take locks on every page that you
touch on the way down
so then when the next right comes
through it might be trying to
put it somewhere else so it doesn't
matter if the next right coming through
is going to a different part of the tree
then it's possible for the two of them
to proceed without interfering with each
other
and when you traverse the tree to find
or the algorithm
is trying to figure out where to put the
data in the tree does it always need to
can it go straight to that point or does
it have to
do a similar search each time
generally you always search from the
root for every new operation
okay so there's no quick way to say
this is the last place i put something
this new one is
best placed here
uh well actually in lmdb we do have an
optimization that does that you know if
yeah actually putting in a couple of
elements that are you know that sort
close to each other
or sort next to each other
lmdb will check that
before it goes back to the root you know
so you have a cursor that points to
where you're inserting data
when you insert a new record it'll look
at
what the cursor is currently pointing at
and see if it's
see if it spans
the space that the new record belongs to
and if it does then it'll just stay on
the current page
and if it doesn't then it'll fall back
to what it has to do it'll go back to
the root and search its way down
and
do you fall back to
searching the whole route to
the last leaf if that cursor
breaks or something happens to it
or do you just trust the fact that it
points to the last
place something was put
well in lmdb it
since there's no other writers
interfering with it then yeah the cursor
always points to so that's another good
reason to have one writer exactly yeah
as i said it simplifies so many things
that you know in my opinion it wasn't
worth the headaches of
maintaining
all the other state needed to do
the multi-page locking
yeah it's like having an
m plus one back out for the backup for
the backup the backup you know
how deep you go
how deep will you go
[Music]
that's one of the problems with the the
approaching berkeley db is that you can
get into lock conflicts very easily um
you know lock conflicts are not
an exceptional unusual condition they're
a routine occurrence
in berkeley db when you have multiple
writers
so
every time you hit a lock conflict
one of the writers
has to give up
release all its locks and retry later
so
if i recall sometimes if there was a
crash there'd be locks left
yeah that's that's another
that's another aspect of things so
that's that's to do with um
you know writing in place versus lmdb's
copy on right but that's not quite
related to the locking issues
so for concurrency management you know
that's that's one approach that and
that's the most common approach that uh
b trees use is the
multi-page locks
that berkeley uses
there's another method which
you know was
relatively recent you know i was reading
about it back in 2009
called a b-link tree
where
leaf nodes contain
link pointers to their siblings
and
by maintaining these link pointers
it actually allows you to do ads and
deletes
with high concurrency without as much
lock overhead
so you know this this was a really
interesting
mechanism when i was reading about it
unfortunately at the time it was very
new research
and there were no working
implementations that i could find
anywhere on the web
and
you know the the research paper that i
read didn't provide me enough
information that i could implement it
myself so so i kind of set it aside
but it was
it was a very promising
paper at the time i think in the years
between then and now there have been at
least two implementations of it
developed of course while it solves some
of the locking problems that we were
just talking about
it doesn't solve the crash problem that
you just mentioned where if something
crashes in the middle then
pages will be lost
yeah and what was the last place right
into and who was doing what yeah yeah
do you think there's
you know you just touched upon
improvements that could be made for
these types of data structures
do you think in 2021 we've reached
the predictable times for
certain things and
the software algorithms these data
structures
and we're now relying on hardware or
just or do you think there'll still be
some major breakthrough breakthroughs
because i know you stay on top of all
this stuff you know i i see a lot of
research into
new algorithms that are
supposed to be
tuned specifically for
you know persistent ram or ssds and thus
and such i find
that
you know the research i've read so far
is not making any
massive breakthroughs and i don't you
know
from that trend i'm not expecting
anything huge
in the future
there's a lot of
small scale refinements is really what
it looks like it's what it amounts to
[Music]
and
what do you think the future is for this
type of data access
uh
well it's
it's gonna be more of the same
you know today we have
a multi-tiered memory hierarchy right
where we talk about cpu caches and then
ram and then
quote storage which is disks or ssds or
whatever
in the future we're going to have
a couple different tiers of ram we'll
have
static ram dynamic ram
persistent ram
i would like to see
further in the future
you know a hundred percent persistent
ram and no more plane dynamic ground but
you know we're not going to get there
yet
we're going to have this intermediate
step first where we have dynamic ram
coexisting with persistent ram and so
that will be another layer of the memory
hierarchy
and
it'll just it's just one more level of a
pyramid
but that won't change the page sizes
that we're dealing with and
it doesn't have to
so the same algorithms could still work
but because the access speeds are faster
it should still be predictably the same
speed or
yeah a generic b plus tree algorithm
will still provide you know optimal
search
as you layer these different memory
technologies above
above each other so that that really
doesn't need to change
page sizes will increase as you
mentioned you know four kilobyte pages
are already
a bit small for today's cpus and
disk subsystems
16 kilobytes is more reasonable
32k
64k would probably be
pushing it
yeah 4k is a bit too small
and is that
some size you have to pick in the b plus
structure or from the software side you
have to use what the hardware supports
so
some cpus today for example
apple's m1 processor are now using 16
kilobyte pages
so
that's the page size that your database
should use as well
so that that means you can
have a shallower tree
yes because you're storing more value
or bigger values
or pointers to the values
more values per page yeah yeah
and which again
speeds up getting things because it's
not so deep
okay
have you ever really been happy with
your project management tool most are
too simple for a growing engineering
team to manage everything or too complex
for anyone to want to use them without
constant product shortcut formerly known
as clubhouse is different though because
it's worse wait no we mean it's better
shortcut is project management built
specifically for software teams it's
fast intuitive flexible powerful and
many other nice positive adjectives
let's look at some highlights team-based
workflows individual teams can use
shortcuts default workflows or customize
them to match the way they work org-wide
goals and roadmaps the work in these
workflows is automatically tied into
larger company goals it takes one click
to move from a roadmap to a team's work
to individual updates and vice versa vcs
integrations whether you use github
gitlab or bitbucket shortcut ties
directly to them so you can update
progress from the command line the rest
of shortcut is just as keyboard friendly
with their power bar allowing you to do
virtually anything without touching your
mouse throw that thing in the trash
iterations planning set weekly
priorities and then let shortcut run the
schedule for you with accompanying
burndown charts and other reporting give
it a try at shortcut.com sc radio again
that's shortcut.com se radio shortcut
again formerly known as clubhouse
because you shouldn't have to project
manage your project management
[Music]
i'd like to start wrapping up i think
we've
done a pretty good job on that let's
just round off with the description of
my b-plus tree again because we've
progressed a little bit so correct me on
this this is a knobbed off internet
just confirm for me in the b plus tree
copies of the keys are stored in the
internal nodes
the keys and records are stored in
leaves in addition a leaf node may
include a pointer to the next leaf node
to speed sequential access
so
are we calling the nodes pages there or
in that place yes the nodes are pages
yes yeah why did it make sense to use
the word page when everything else
uses nodes for the previous data
structures
the the word page is associated with
virtual memory management and disk
management
and that's what we're trying to improve
here that's relying the data on top of
the disks
yeah ssds
excellent
okay so obviously selection of the
correct data structures
to use is extremely important to us
software engineers and companies but if
there was one thing from
this journey of an episode you would
want our listeners to remember what
would you like that to be
i would say
most of the time
for your data management needs
you're just gonna need a b plus tree and
you can ignore anything else
perfect
and don't try and do it yourself there
should be a library for it
yeah
um was there anything we missed that
you'd like to mention
we did cover quite a lot
we covered a lot around here so i think
we're good
excellent so
where can people find out more about
your b3 plus yeah i get it right b plus
3 work or what you're working on
obviously we've got your twitter account
i will link to
um but i'm sure if people are interested
they can
look into the source code of lmdb and
get their head around how you've done v
plus tree
sure yeah and also um
the lmdb.tech
website has the
uh formatted documentation online so
you can read through that there
while you're browsing through the source
code
thank you i'll put that in the show
notes
so
this show personally has really helped
me understand b trees hopefully the
listeners
will come off a little bit better than
when they started listening
they're less confused yeah so howard
thank you for coming on the show it's
been a real pleasure this is gavin henry
for software engineering radio thank you
for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening